<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<article>
  <articleinfo>
    <title>Liquid Crystal Display (16 characters x 2 rows).</title>

    <author>
      <firstname>Bert</firstname>

      <surname>Timmerman</surname>

      <affiliation>
        <orgname><trademark>Me, organised ???</trademark></orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
  </articleinfo>

  <section>
    <title>Liquid Crystal - "hello world!".</title>

    <para>The LiquidCrystal library allows you to control LCD displays that
    are compatible with the Hitachi HD44780 driver.</para>

    <para>There are many LCD displays out there, and you can usually tell them
    by the 16-pin interface.</para>

    <para>This example sketch prints "Hello World!" to the LCD and shows the
    time in seconds since the Arduino was reset.</para>

    <figure>
      <title>Output of the sketch on a 2x16 LCD</title>

      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="../../../../../../sketchbook/Main/LCD16x2/docs/LCD16x2_photo.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    <para>The LCDs have a parallel interface, meaning that the microcontroller
    has to manipulate several interface pins at once to control the
    display.</para>

    <para>The interface consists of the following pins:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>A register select (RS) pin that controls where in the LCD's
        memory you're writing data to.</para>

        <para>You can select either the data register, which holds what goes
        on the screen, or an instruction register, which is where the LCD's
        controller looks for instructions on what to do next.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A Read/Write (R/W) pin that selects reading mode or writing
        mode.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>An Enable pin that enables writing to the registers.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>8 data pins (D0 -D7). The states of these pins (high or low) are
        the bits that you're writing to a register when you write, or the
        values you're reading when you read.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>A display contrast pin (Vo).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Power supply pins (+5V and Gnd) and LED Backlight (Bklt+ and
        BKlt-) pins that you can use to power the LCD, control the display
        contrast, and turn on and off the LED backlight, respectively.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>The process of controlling the display involves putting the data
    that form the image of what you want to display into the data registers,
    then putting instructions in the instruction register.</para>

    <para>The LiquidCrystal Library simplifies this for you so you don't need
    to know the low-level instructions.</para>

    <para>The Hitachi-compatible LCDs can be controlled in two modes: 4-bit or
    8-bit.</para>

    <para>The 4-bit mode requires seven I/O pins from the Arduino, while the
    8-bit mode requires 11 pins.</para>

    <para>For displaying text on the screen, you can do most everything in
    4-bit mode, so example shows how to control a 2x16 LCD in 4-bit
    mode.</para>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Hardware Required.</title>

    <para/>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Arduino Board</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>LCD Screen (compatible with Hitachi HD44780 driver)</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>10k Potentiometer</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>breadboard</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>hook-up wire</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Circuit.</title>

    <para>To wire your LCD screen to your Arduino, connect the following
    pins:<itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>LCD RS pin to Arduino digital pin 12</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>LCD Enable pin to Arduino digital pin 11</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>LCD D4 pin to Arduino digital pin 5</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>LCD D5 pin to Arduino digital pin 4</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>LCD D6 pin to Arduino digital pin 3</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>LCD D7 pin to Arduino digital pin 2</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>fixed terminals of the 10K pot to +5V and GND</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>wiper of the 10K pot (output) to LCD screens VO pin
          (pin3)</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <para><figure>
        <title>Schematic.</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="LCD16x2_schematic.png" width="600"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure><figure>
        <title>Wiring.</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="LCD16x2_bb.png" width="600"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure></para>
  </section>
</article>
